Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes, 1
  - Animals: J. D. the noble king of beasts. (Offsite-box 1, Item 7)
    First two lines of text under the image of a lion, the next two under the image of a zebra. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Ridenburgh, William, copyright holder
  - Animals: A southern gorrilla, (guerilla). A southern gorilla, (guerilla) (Offsite-box 1, Item 2)
    Gorilla (?) dressed in uniform with Confederate hat. White envelope with black ink. Image on left, text top-center.
  - Animals: A confederated chicken. (Offsite-box 1, Item 33)
    A chicken missing most of its feathers with a small sword suspended from it's body. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: New-York Union Envelope Depot New -York Union Envelope Deport New-York Union Envelope Deport
  - Animals: O Jeff! You little noisy cur! (Offsite-box 1, Item 40)
    A Union soldier on horseback ropes a dog labeled "mad." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left (vertical orientation.)
  - Animals: Free speech at the South. (Offsite-box 1, Item 84)
    A nude female crouches and covers her head with her arms to protect herself from a snake, labeled "secession," that entwines her body, rising over her with a hissing open mouth. Envelope of orange paper with black ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Root or Die (Offsite-box 1, Item 89)
    Pig with saddle holding American flag rooting under the Secession rock. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Animals: To the South. (Offsite-box 1, Item 51)
    A bird in flight carrying message in its beak. White envelope with blue ink. Image in top-left.
  - Animals: [Secession as a dragon] (Offsite-box 1, Item 53)
    A knight wearing the American shield fights a dragon labeled "secession." White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: The moaning of the tied. (Offsite-box 1, Item 41)
    A howling dog tied to a post. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: Strayed. (Offsite-box 1, Item 12)
    A lion approaches a frightened mule as a man in uniform limps off nearby. White envelope with black ink.
  - Animals: The southern vulture "hard up." (Offsite-box 1, Item 39)
    Confederate soldier with rooster's head entering a pawn shop carrying a bail of cotton. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Hornet's nest. (Offsite-box 1, Item 73)
    Hornets nest in tree branches. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: The flower of the South. (Offsite-box 1, Item 11)
    A mule's head on the body of a well-dressed man. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Young America preparing a "Hasty Plate of Soup" for Gen. Scott. (Offsite-box 1, Item 91)
    The motto tells who is who in the drawing. Turtles and other animals are slaughtered by 'Young America'. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
  - Animals: Massachusetts vs. South Carolina. (Offsite-box 1, Item 21)
    Two cats, tied together by their tales and hung upside-down over a branch, fighting with one another. One cat is labeled "S. Carolina," the other "Massachusetts." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Governor Magoffin's neutrality means holding the Cock of the Walk while the Confederate Cat kills off his chickens. (Offsite-box 1, Item 34)
    A cat, labeled "Magoffin," holds back a rooster, labeled "Uncle Sam," as another cat, labeled "Jeff Davis," kills chicks labeled "Union." White envelope with red ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: The union constitution liberty and laws!! (Offsite-box 1, Item 60)
    Elephant carrying an American flag with the words "The union constitution liberty and laws!!", and wearing another flag on its back, lifts it foot over a running rat labeled "Jeff." White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Mumford & Co., publisher
  - Animals: The Hercules of 1861. (Offsite-box 1, Item 74)
    General Grant (?) swings a club labeled "Union" in defense against a many-headed serpent labeled "Secession." The serpent's heads are: Floyd, Pickens, Beauregard, Twiggs, Davis, Stephens, and Toombs. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: Floyd, of the C.S.A. (Offsite-box 1, Item 79)
    A raccoon. White envelope with blue ink. Image in top left corner.
  - Animals: The Speaker of the House of the "Southern Confederacy," now assembled, July 20th, 1861. (Offsite-box 1, Item 3)
    A monkey sitting on a chair. He is wearing clothes and smoking. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left (vertical orientation).
  - Animals: Beef for the rebels. (Offsite-box 1, Item 4)
    Alligator on the banks of a river. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: Sly-fox Scott. (Offsite-box 1, Item 63)
    Monkey, labeled "Jeff," holding a Confederate flag playing cards with a fox beside an American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: I wonder if the coast is clear? (Offsite-box 1, Item 22)
    Cats wearing military hats and epaulettes sit on bails of cotton in a blockaded harbor. They kill rats which are labeled " prizes." White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Animals: "Let us Alone." (Offsite-box 1, Item 88)
    Large pig standing. White envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Berlin & Jones, copyright holder
  - Animals: National Veal Weal (Offsite-box 1, Item 95)
    A large beaver holds up a steel trap over a weasel with "Jeff" over his head. Weasel has a broom and pail tied to his tail. Yellow envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Animals: Spirit of the North (Offsite-box 1, Item 76)
    A lion in a field. White envelope with green and yellow ink. Image in top left corner.
    Creator: J. Magee
  - Animals: Secession Web (Offsite-box 1, Item 86)
    Davis as a spider catching the secession states in his web strung from the American flag. There is a skull and cross bones on his spider back and he is dripping blood and clutching Virginia. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Animals: The End of Rebellion-a painful Tail (Offsite-box 1, Item 99)
    Scissors labeled 'Union Shears' cutting off the tail of the animal labeled Secession while 'Secession' is jumping out of an open window. A hand holds the severed tail. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: D. Murphy's son, printer
  - Animals: A rara (D) avis wants to be let alone. (Offsite-box 1, Item 38)
    Rooster pins another bird labeled "C. S. A." on its back as the pinned bird exclaims "Oh! Let me alone." Pink envelope with black ink. Image in top-left. Embossed decoration on seal.
  - Animals: An ass-sault from a "masked" battery. (Offsite-box 1, Item 13)
    Soldier being kicked by a rearing mule. White envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Animals: Here Lies C.S.A. (Offsite-box 1, Item 98)
    Tombstone for the C.S.A. Appears to be a mule head and an African-American sitting atop the mules head. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Constitution: E Pluribus Unum (Offsite-box 2, Item 20)
    Temple of Liberty on a hill entitled Constitution and Laws, with people waving the American flag below. White envelope with red, blue and brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Constitution: The Constitution (Offsite-box 2, Item 8)
    Hands shaking over the background of the Constitution, American flag, a battle-axe and stars. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Death's Head: Oh! "Let me Alone." (Offsite-box 2, Item 2)
    A mock shield coat of arms. A serpent forms the border, with a crowned skull and crossbones in the center, over a bottle of whiskey. White envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Death's Head: Weighed, and found wanting (Offsite-box 2, Item 25)
    Omnipotent eye in the sky and disembodied hand holding scales. Scales have skull on crossbones on lighter side and the battle-axe of the Union on the heavier side. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Death's Head: Monument to the memory of Jeff. Davis (Offsite-box 2, Item 29)
    Jefferson Davis as a skeleton in military boots, sword and hat standing atop a stacked pyramid of skulls. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Death's Head: Secession Whiskey (Offsite-box 2, Item 26)
    A giant goblet being hovered over by a skeleton. Inside the goblet is a pudgy, drunk (sleeping?) person. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Death's Head: Vanity, Treachery & Death (Offsite-box 2, Item 24)
    Skull, with serpent wrapping around it and a feather. White envelope with black ink. Image on top left side.
  - Flags--Confederate: We are Seven (Offsite-box 2, Item 1)
    Flag of South Carolina with palmetto on it. Beige envelope with black ink. Image on top left side.
  - Flags--Confederate: [Confederate flag] (Offsite-box 2, Item 3)
    Confederate flag. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Flags--Confederate: May emblems of traitors, ever scurvy Be forever topsy-turvy. (Offsite-box 2, Item 10)
    Confederate flag, upside down. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Flags--Confederate: The Pirate Flag (Offsite-box 2, Item 6)
    Confederate flag with the 'The Pirate Flag' in blue section and Davis and Stephens on red bars. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image covers entire envelope.
  - Flags--Union: Richmond has fallen! (Offsite-box 2, Item 70)
    American flag with the words "Richmond has fallen" on it. Design covers entirety of white envelope in red and blue ink. Handwritten date of April 18, 1914 on the back.
  - Flags--Union: The Union Forever (Offsite-box 2, Item 31)
    Waving American flag on a pole. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Flags--Union: The Constitution and the Union (Offsite-box 2, Item 8)
  - Flags--Union: The Stars and Stripes must cover the whole (Offsite-box 2, Item 62)
    A map of the United States with the flag covering the entirety of it. Design takes up the entire back of the white envelope. Ink used is red, blue and black.
  - Flags--Union: Our compromise for Traitors (Offsite-box 2, Item 51)
    Waving American flag with circular star pattern. Smoking cannon, to indicate it's just been fired below the flag. Yellow envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: No Foreign Interference (Offsite-box 2, Item 22)
    A floral design of cotton with a decorative border. White envelope with red, blue, green and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: JOHN,-I Paid the cash for this cotton and want to pass? (Offsite-box 2, Item 6)
    John Bull is hauling a large bale of cotton on his back. Uncle Sam tells him he 'can't pass Joney'. Man on left has a bag of money and a cat of nine tails whip. Cream envelope with black ink. Large image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Great Safe Trial (Offsite-box 2, Item 26)
    John Bull and Napoleon characters stand in front of two safes that have had fires set underneath them. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: John Bull in his perilous feat of Horsemanship (Offsite-box 2, Item 23)
    John Bull tries to ride two horses, the Union and Secession while balancing a bale of cotton on his shoulders. Beige envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Cotton - England's God (Offsite-box 2, Item 19)
    A large crowned head with a small body sits atop a bale of cotton, with many people kneeling and worshipping around it. 'King Cotton' is sitting and crushing slaves. White envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Cotton is King! (Offsite-box 2, Item 16)
    John Bull with a paper printed with 'Manchester' in his pocket kneels before a large, crowned anthropomorphic bale of cotton. The man Bull is stepping on a slave on the ground. White envelope with many colored ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: John Bull (Offsite-box 2, Item 30)
    A clothed bull stands in a doorway talking to a man (perhaps William L. Yancey?) with a paper with 'Bogus' printed on it. A bale of cotton stands nearby. Envelope is white with blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Stimson & Co.
  - Foreign Affairs: Commissioners of C.S.A. at the Foreign Courts. (Offsite-box 2, Item 2)
    Babies dressed in finery playing with each other. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: John Bull "don't see it." (Offsite-box 2, Item 29)
    John Bull looks into a viewing device is a bale of cotton while cotton in dumped into his vision path. An African-American child holds up a sign with "Southern Vi…". Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: J.D.--Please let me bring my prizes on to your premises, Mr. Bull. (Offsite-box 2, Item 5)
    John Bull stands in doorway while Davis tries to give him things in a large satchel. 'Yankee Doodle' looks on from atop a fence. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: These bonds will never do, my friend (Offsite-box 2, Item 27)
    Man standing with two papers in his hands, one saying "Southern Bonds" the other "Jeff Davis $20,000". Two men stand in the background, one under a sign "Loans Taken". Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: New York Union Envelope Depot
  - Foreign Affairs: Victoria Rex thinks better of it and won't recognise traitors or harbo(u)r their pirate-eers (Offsite-box 2, Item 31)
    A figure with a Union Jack shield (Queen Victoria as England) sits on a lion. Below is a rooster saying "Now won't you recognise us!" Rooster holds a Confederate flag with a skull stuck on it. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Brown & Ryan
  - Foreign Affairs: John Bull making his speech to "King Cotton" (Offsite-box 2, Item 25)
    John Bull character standing, with one hand in his pocket. Beige envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Jeff announceth to ye rebell Cabinett ye grayte scheme of invytynge Grayte Brittayne to send our a Royall Babbie to take chge of ye Cottonocracy of ye South-ye whych produceth mutch merrymeant among ye Cabinett aforesayd. (Offsite-box 2, Item 28)
    A table full of men writing with pen and ink and looking amused. White envelope with red ink. Image takes up entire envelope.
  - Foreign Affairs: The British Lion heedless of the trap (Offsite-box 2, Item 8)
    A lion creeps toward a trap set using cotton as a bait. The string is held by a man dressed in military garb, with a man in top hat and tails sitting on a rock to the right. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Harpel, printer
  - Foreign Affairs: John Bull's Sympathy (Offsite-box 2, Item 14)
    A slave is being whipped as he kneels beside a bale of cotton imprinted with CSA on it. John Bull sits atop the bale ignoring the kneeling slave near him. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Jeff.--I want to be "let a loan" on these little collaterals. (Offsite-box 2, Item 3)
    Jefferson Davis trying to get a loan from John Bull for what appears to be cherries. White envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Foreign Affairs: Look out John or you will get your foot in it (Offsite-box 2, Item 10)
    A bull (John) sticking his foot in a trap entitled Secession. The eagle warns him not to step in it. The Rooster with epaulets, Napoleon, tells him Bravo.
  - Foreign Affairs: The Reverses of the C.S.A. (Offsite-box 2, Item 1)
    Man's face that appears smiling when envelope held upright and frowning when envelope is flipped over. Two sets of text each appears under each 'face'. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Fort Sumter: Remember Fort Sumter! (Offsite-box 2, Item 14)
    Large American flag flying over a burning Fort Sumter. Beige envelope with red, blue and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Fort Sumter: Ft. Sumpter [sic] (Offsite-box 2, Item 6)
    The figure of Liberty dressed in the stars and stripes rises in a cloud over Ft. Sumter. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Fort Sumter: Though seven rebel forts combined (Offsite-box 2, Item 2)
    A scene of Fort Sumter ablaze with a large flag waving overhead. Yellow envelope with red, blue and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Fort Sumter: "Sumter First-Peace Afterwards." (Offsite-box 2, Item 11)
    Figure of Victory on the shore holding the flag, points toward Ft. Sumter and a ship in the water behind her. It appears some sort of lightning bolt is coming toward the flag on Ft. Sumter. Beige envelope with red and blue ink. Image on top left side.
  - Liberty/Columbia: Liberty at Port Royal (Offsite-box 2, Item 17)
    Liberty standing on a cannon with the flag waving next to her. A ship is in the background. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image is on top and left.
  - Liberty/Columbia: The Traitors shall have Justice. (Offsite-box 2, Item 4)
    A figure of Justice with scales and sword leaning against a pillar. Orange envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Ridenburgh, William, distributor
  - Liberty/Columbia: [Liberty] (Offsite-box 2, Item 23)
    Liberty dressed in stars and stripes holding wheat and reaching up towards the flag that says Union. White envelope with many colored inks. Image on left side.
  - Liberty/Columbia: [Liberty and a Native American] (Offsite-box 2, Item 40)
    The figure of Liberty holding a flag alongside a Native American. White envelope with multi-colored image. Image on left side.
    Creator: Kimmel, F. K.
  - Liberty/Columbia: Justice shall be done (Offsite-box 2, Item 8)
    Figure of Justice with scales and sword. Beige envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 5)
    Nine soldiers, one on horseback, in various uniforms, posed near a tent. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 3)
    Seven soldiers in various uniforms posed among trees. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Magnus, Charles
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 19)
    Nine soldiers in various uniforms posed with crossing bayonets. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 8)
    Seven soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tent and a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 7)
    Four soldiers in various uniforms, one on horseback, posed near a tent. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 16)
    Soldier posed with his rifle in front of a tree. Soldiers on horseback in the background. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 1)
    Five soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 10)
    Seven soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tent and a tall gas lamp. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 9)
    Five soldiers in various uniforms, one on horseback, posed near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 12)
    Five soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tent with a tall gas lamp nearby. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 15)
    Nine soldiers in various uniforms posed with crossing bayonets among some trees. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 13)
    Seven soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tent labeled "refreshments" with a tall gas lamp nearby. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 11)
    Six soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 17)
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 2)
    Six soldiers in uniform posed around a tent labeled "refreshments." White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 4)
    Four soldiers in various uniforms posed near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 18)
    Eight soldiers in various uniforms posed with crossing bayonets.White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 6)
    Six soldiers in various uniforms posed with crossing bayonets, near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 20)
    Ten soldiers in various uniforms posed outdoors. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Camp Scene: Camp scene from photograph (Offsite-box 3, Item 14)
    Four soldiers in various uniforms, one on horseback, posed near a tree. White envelope with cooper-colored ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: Gen. L. Blenker (Offsite-box 3, Item 48)
    Portrait of Louis Blenker with a map of Virginia. Image covers sheet. White envelope with gold ink.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: Maj. Gen. McCall (Offsite-box 3, Item 76)
    Portrait of McCall surrounded by soldiers. Cream envelope with gold ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: Review of the army. (Offsite-box 3, Item 10)
    Portraits of Abraham Lincoln and George McClellan framed by flags and soldiers in various uniforms. White envelope with gold ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: [Portrait of a group of Union soldiers] (Offsite-box 3, Item 30)
    Large group portrait of a number of Union soldiers, some on horseback. Cream envelope with gold ink. Image covers entire front of envelope.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: [Portrait of a group of Union soldiers] (Offsite-box 3, Item 32)
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: [Portrait of a group of Union soldiers] (Offsite-box 3, Item 31)
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: Maj. Gen. Halleck (Offsite-box 3, Item 74)
    Portrait of Henry Halleck surrounded by soldiers. Cream envelope with gold ink. Image on left.
  - Magnus, Charles--Portraits: Maj. Gen. Butler (Offsite-box 3, Item 49)
    Benjamin Butler beside a map of North Carolina. White envelope with green ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Magnus, Charles--Star Spangled Banner: [Train with flag.] (Offsite-box 3, Item 1)
    Train flying American flag on front of locomotive. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left. Verso: Lyrics to "The Star Spangled Banner."
  - Magnus, Charles--States: New York. (Offsite-box 3, Item 30)
    Soldiers on battlefield on left. New York state seal on top-center. American Flag on left. White envelope with gold ink.
    Creator: Magnus, Charles, publisher